The Final Problem
1891年春天 当我从一个短暂的休假
When I returned to Baker Street
回到贝克街的时候
from a short holiday in the spring of 1891,
我只见到过福尔摩斯没几次
I had seen little of Holmes for some time.
我从报纸上获悉 他受聘于法国政府
I saw in the papers that he had been engaged
承办一件极为重要的案子
by the French government upon a matter of supreme importance
但是 出乎我预计的是
but I could hardly foresee that it would have
这居然会产生如此可怕的后果
so violent a consequence.
现在必须由我来告知
It lies with me now to tell for the first time
在那决定性的一年 发生在
what took place between Mr. Sherlock Holmes
福尔摩斯和莫里亚蒂教授之间的事
and Professor Moriarity in that fateful year.
啊 哈德森太太 福尔摩斯先生回来了吗?
Ah, Mrs. Hudson has Mr. Holmes returned?
哦 他已经回来了
Oh, he has indeed.
他很早就来了
He came in early.
应该是7点之前
Must have been before 7:00.
他说 早啊 哈德森太太
"Morning Mrs. Hudson" he says,
给我准备了些什么美味的早餐没?
"Have you anything nice for my breakfast?"
好像他四个月里根本没离开过
as if he hadn't been away for four months.
你本来可以让我大吃一惊的
You could have knocked me down with a feather.
那我猜他马上又出去了?
And he's gone out again I take it?
是的 是的 他吃完早餐就又出去了
Yes, yes he had his breakfast and then he went out again
就在他的拜访者离开后不久
just after his visitor left.
拜访者?
Visitor?
一个上了年纪的人
An elderly gentleman.
他们还吵了几句
They had words.
我不喜欢那人的长相 一点都不喜欢
I didn't like the look of him, not at all I didn't.
他的表情带着上帝的愤怒
He had a face like, like the wrath of God
更甚是恶魔的愤怒
or should I say the devil.
的确
Indeed.
我们是否应该开一瓶顶级红酒
Should we open a bottle of the best claret
来庆祝福尔摩斯先生的回归?
to celebrate Mr. Holmes' return?
为什么不呢?
Why not?
很好
Very good.
谢谢你 哈德森太太
Thank you, Mrs. Hudson.
我后来才知道 福尔摩斯先生在那天
I learned later that Holmes had survived three attempts
已经三次从试图取他性命的预谋中逃脱
on his life that very day.
但在我等待他回家之际时
But as I waited for him to reappear
我眼中的贝克街一如既往的平和安宁
Baker Street looked to me as safe and secure as ever.
福尔摩斯 你...
Holmes you...
等等 等等
Wait, wait.
这是什么
What is it?
气枪 事实上 是一把非常特别的气枪
Air guns, a rather special air gun in fact.
华生 你不反对把窗帘拉上吧?
Watson would you have any objection to drawing
随意点 装成好像只有你独自在这房间
the blinds casually as if you were alone in this room?
我想你对我是非常了解的 华生 你知道
Watson I think you know me well enough to understand
我并不是一个胆小怕事的人
that I am by no means a nervous man.
可如果你危险临头还不承认有危险
But it is stupidity rather than courage
那就是有勇无谋了
to refuse to recognize danger when it is close upon you.
该死
Damn!
华生 能给我根火柴吗?
Watson, might I have a match?
福尔摩斯 你受伤了
Holmes, you're hurt.
划伤而已 没事的
Scratches, nothing, nothing to signify.
你看起来不太好 福尔摩斯
You don't look well Holmes.
近来我把自己搞得过于精疲力尽了
Well I have been using myself rather too freely.
最近我有点儿吃紧
I have been somewhat pressed but late.
怎么了?
How pressed?
既然我在天黑前不可能离开这房间
Well as I am unable to leave this room until after dark
也不可能走回我来的那条路
and then most likely on the way that I came,
我们现在有足够的时间
we do have some time on our hands.
自从上次见面后 我还欠你一个
Also I owe you an explanation for my unceremonious departure
不告而别的解释
the last time that we met.
我想记些笔记 可以吗?
I'll take some notes if I may?
哦 当然
Oh, by all means.
这个案子
This case...
这个案子 在犯罪年鉴上
This case, it is unique
是很罕见的
in the annuals of crime.
你还记得我年初离开贝克街的时间
You will recall that it was a cold morning early in the year
是一个寒冷的早晨吗
when I last left Baker Street.
我对自己的去处和委托人身份毫不知情
I had no idea where I was going or who my client was.
我所知道的就是 这非常重要
All I knew was that it was important
并且发生在国外
and abroad.
我的目的地就是巴黎的卢浮宫和博物馆
My destination was the museum and the Louve was in Paris
而我的委托人 正是法国政府
and my client none less than the French government.
卢浮宫可以称得上是法国的心脏
Surely this Louve is near to the very heart of France.
伟大的法官就在这里开庭审理
It was here that the great Musele held court
也是拿破仑
and here that Napoleon Bonaparte
和皇女
was married to the Archduchess Madam
奥地利公主玛丽・路易丝结婚的地方
Marie Louise of Austria.
这里正是历史的纪念碑
Indeed it is a history lesson in stone.
现在 画廊拥有着世上最优秀的作品
And now this gallery contains our finest paintings.
先生们 我们能不能直奔主题?
Gentlemen, shall we come to the point?
我推测蒙娜丽莎被偷了
I presume the Mona Lisa has been stolen.
当我看到原来悬挂蒙娜丽莎的墙壁
When I see two hooks and the place where
以及那两个挂钩 再加上这些
the Mona Lisa used to hang and then this talk
八卦一类的谈话
of... and scandal.
我终于有点明白这件事的谨慎之因了
Yes, now I begin to understand the delicacy of the matter.
卢浮宫每周一都会闭馆整顿
The Louve is closed on Mondays for maintenance.
蒙娜丽莎没有被悬挂在原处
The fact that the Mona Lisa was not hanging
无疑是因为
in her usual place was no doubt due to the fact
它曾被带去一个摄影工作室
that she was in the photographic studio.
仅仅一天之后 一个工人
It was only later in the day that a workman found the frame
在展览馆的某小储藏室里发现了画框
in a little storeroom under the salon care.
我们在一个月前
We put the glass over the painting
才刚刚给画像安上玻璃
only a month ago.
防止它被酸侵蚀 最近
We feared an acid attack, there was such a one
在佛罗伦萨就发生了这种事
in Florence recently.
真是幸运啊
How very fortunate.
你说什么
Pardon?
有两个清晰的指纹
Two good thumb prints.
许多艺术家来这制作复制品
Many artists come here to make copies of the paintings.
这幅模仿得极像
This one seems well done.
是的 那个艺术家极具天赋
Yes, that artist is particularly clever
并且凭借他的复制才能过着优渥的生活
and makes a good living from his copying.
我想见见他
I should like to meet him sometime.
做一件失败的复制品非常简单 反之
To make a bad copy is very easy but a good one,
则需要多年的练习
it takes years of practice.
例如 达・芬奇
For instance De Vinci
他用意大利木来作画
used Italian popular wood to paint on.
这种材料非常少见
It is very difficult to find.
想要和原来的颜色一致 几乎是不可能的
To match the original color, nearly impossible.
这是非常成熟的作品 色调流畅柔和
It is, uh, full mature, the smooth blended tones,
非常精妙 还有他的笔法
very subtle and his brushwork
他是左手作画的
is left-handed.
那些断痕 那些完美
The crack work, this fine network
断痕的交叉 看左边
of cracks, left, ah.
要想模仿全部是非常困难的
that is the most difficult to achieve of all.
可是你可以?
And you can achieve it?
你是如何做到的?
How?
那是我的秘密
That is my secret.
在我看来 这并不能算是
It seems to me that this is something
合法伪造
near to a legitimate forgery.
不 不 不 因为这些复制品和原作
No, no, no because the copies must never
并不是同一尺寸
be the same size as the original.
再说 既然真正的蒙娜丽莎还在卢浮宫
And, and who would buy one of my copies as the original
谁会来买我的复制品呢
when the real Mona Lisa is in the Louve.
但是 如果蒙娜丽莎恰巧
But if by chance the Mona Lisa
不在卢浮宫了呢?
is no longer in the Louve?
显然你是在说笑
But of course you are joking Messier.
幸好法国警察在指纹检测方面
Happily the French police are well ahead of the British
比英国的要出色
when it comes to fingerprints.
伟大的班逊是如此谦逊
The great Bantion himself was kind enough to refer
将我的嫌犯小册子当作他的圣经
to my little pamphlet on the subject as his bible.
如我怀疑的 嫌犯过去曾
As I suspected, our man had been involved
犯下轻罪  他叫门德萨 西班牙人
in petty crime in the past, a Spaniard named Mendosa.
看 他就是你们要找的小偷
There, there is your thief.
一看就不是善类
Not a pleasant specimen.
福尔摩斯先生 法国人欠你一个人情
Mr. Holmes, France owes you a great debt.
我们还没有抓住这个人 更重要的是
We have not got the man and more important,
那副画也没找到
the painting.
但是 他必须马上被逮捕
But he must be arrested immediately.
他很有可能已经把画卖了
He may have already sold it.
不 不 先生们 我相信
No, no, gentlemen it is my belief
那幅画还在门德萨手上
that the painting is still in Mendosa's keeping.
他只是大阴谋中的其中一粒小棋子
He is only a pawn in a much bigger game.
偷窃是经过周密计划的
This robbery has been carefully planned
策划者已计划了数月甚至数年
over months, even years by a master criminal.
但什么样的职业罪犯
But what professional criminal would want
会想要拥有蒙娜丽莎呢?
to own the Mona Lisa?
真是疯狂
That is madness.
他又不能卖掉
He can't sell it.
我相信这个犯罪头目对原作
I believe the master criminal is not interested
没有兴趣
in the original,
如果他能以赝品冒充原作
if he can pass off the forgeries as originals
以相同价格出售
for the same price.
先生们 我们必须警告门德萨
Gentlemen we must alarm Mendosa,
让他行动起来 带领我们
get him on the move so he leads us
走进这张犯罪网络的中心
to the center of the web.
但要怎样做呢?
But how?
首先 我们必须向世界宣布
First we must announce to the world
这幅画已经被偷了
that the painting has been stolen.
但是那会给
Oh, but that would create
我和警长带来莫大的丑闻
a great scandal both myself and the director of...
部长 请听我解释
Minister, please if I may explain.
同时还宣布 凭借你和警长的智慧
It would be announced that owing to the brilliant
以及不懈的努力
and tireless efforts of yourself and the director,
罪犯即将落网
that the criminal is about to be arrested.
福尔摩斯先生 我们必须现在就逮捕他
Mr. Holmes, we must arrest him now.
不
No.
现在
Now!
福尔摩斯 我明白无论复制品多么优秀
Holmes, I understand that the recovery of the original
只要原作一找回
would make it impossible for the thieves to sell
窃贼就无法出售复制品
any copies however excellent those copies were,
但是 你到底有没有任何关于
but did you have any clue to the identity
这个阴谋主使者的线索?
of the mastermind behind the whole scheme?
我很庆幸我认识
I was satisfied that I had recognized one of
莫里亚蒂教授的代理人之一
Professor Moriarity's agents.
莫里亚蒂?
Moriarity?
请注意这画对人物特征的精妙刻画
Notice the subtle modeling of the features,
美丽的双手
beautiful hands,
安详的神情
mood,
那微笑
that smile.
如同华特・培顿所形容的
As Walter Payton described her,
美颜在上 世界黯然失色
the head upon which all the ends of the world are common.
眼睑有一丝疲倦
The eyelids are a little weary.
没有人拥有
No one else has ever had
如此出神入化的绘画技巧 除了达・芬奇
the genius to paint this masterpiece except De Vinci.
再来看看这幅画作
But if you look at the paint work sir.
里奥纳多飘逸的签名 笔工精湛
Leonard's signature at large, the brush work,
收放自如 技巧娴熟
the bloom, the technique.
不好意思 失陪
Will you excuse me?
我可以肯定地告诉你
I would say without hesitation that the general opinion
这是艺术节公认的
of the art world is that this
世上最伟大的肖像作品
is the greatest portrait ever painted.
我很遗憾地告诉你 先生
I very much regret to have to tell you sir
这画我们不卖了
that this painting is no longer for sale.
我不明白 教授
I don't understand Professor.
难道是价格太低吗?
I mean, the price maybe?
我可以重新考虑
Well now look, I'll reconsider.
我会付你4百万 怎么样?
I'll give you a cool four million and how's that?
我很抱歉 沃克先生
I'm sorry Mr. Walker,
这画现在是非卖品
the painting is no longer for sale.
嘿 你们这帮人在搞什么啊?
Hey, what you guys up to?
把你的脏手拿开 你个混蛋!
Take your hands off me you nick!
谢谢你们浪费时间
Thanks for nothing.
那个该死的福尔摩斯已经找回原作了
That wretched Holmes has recovered the original.
这些东西都是垃圾了
These are worthless.
毁了他们
Destroy them,
烧掉
burn them.
你亲自做
Do it yourself,
不要让任何人看见
and let no one else see you.
遵命 莫里亚蒂教授
Yes, Professor Moriarity.
恭喜你 福尔摩斯
I must congratulate you, Holmes.
这等荣誉是你应得的
Such an honor and so well deserved.
我其实也没做什么
There was no great problem.
这个案子基本上是自动解决的
The case practically solved itself.
我听说你今天早上有个拜访者
I hear you had a visitor this morning.
噢!
Ow!
我回到贝克街
I had not been back in Baker Street
刚坐下不到半小时 就在这时...
more than half an hour when...
你不能上去 先生!
But you cannot go up there sir!
你的前额
You have less frontal development
不如我想象中那样发达
than I should have expected.
摆弄睡衣口袋里子弹上膛的手枪
It's a dangerous habit, a finger loaded firearms
是一个危险的习惯
in the pocket of one's dressing gown.
你显然不了解我
You evidentially don't know me.
恰恰相反 我认为我对你十分了解
On the contrary I think it's fairly evident that I do.
如果有什么话要说 我可以给你5分钟
I can spare you five minutes if you have anything to say.
我所要说的你都已经心知肚明了
All that I have to say has already crossed your mind.
而我的回答你也已经心知肚明
And possibly my answer has already crossed yours.
你决不让步?
You stand fast?
绝不
Absolutely.
在法国一事上
You frustrated me in the affair
你妨碍了我
of the French gold.
原来红头联盟的幕后黑手是你啊
So it was you behind the Red Headed League.
真是一个极具创造性和挑战性的点子啊
A very ingenious and welcome tried idea.
你抬举我了
High praise from you.
1月4日你阻碍过我行事
You crossed my path first on the 4th of January.
2月中旬你给我制造了很大麻烦
By the middle of February I was seriously inconvenienced
而在3月底
by you and at the end of March
你完全破坏了我的计划
I was absolutely hampered in my plans.
现在你又妨碍了我在法国的最后一桩买卖
And now with this last business in France you have placed me
你的不断阻挠 使我面临
in such a position by your continual persecution
有丧失自由的危险
that I am in positive danger of losing my liberty.
事情已经是忍无可忍了
The situation is becoming an impossible one.
你有什么打算吗?
Have you any suggestion to make?
你必须住手 福尔摩斯先生
You must drop it Mr. Holmes.
你知道 你真的必须住手
You really must you know.
如果我拒绝了呢?
And what if I refuse?
我确信 一个如你般智慧的人
I'm quite sure that a man of your intelligence
可以预见 这件事情只能有一个结果
will see that there can be but one outcome to this affair.
那就是你必须住手
It is necessary that you should withdraw.
你把事情做绝了
You have worked things in such a fashion
我们只剩下这一种办法
that we have only one resource left.
看到你把这件事搅成这个样子
It has been an intellectual treat to me to see
这对我来说简直是智力上的一种乐事
the way in which you grappled with this matter.
坦白说 如果我被迫采取任何极端措施
But I say unaffectedly that it would be a grief to me
对我来说 那是令人痛心的
to be forced to take an extreme measure.
你笑吧 先生
Oh, you smile sir
可是我向你保证 那真是令人痛心的
but it really would I do assure you.
干我们这行危险是不可避免的
Danger is part of my trade.
这不是危险
This is not danger.
这是不可避免的毁灭
It is inevitable destruction.
你所阻挠的不单是一个人
You stand in the way not merely of an individual
而是一个强大的组织 其雄厚力量
but of a mighty organization, the full extent of which
即使是用尽你所有的智慧
even you with all your cleverness have been
也无法完全了解
unable to realize.
你必须站开点 福尔摩斯先生
You must stand clear Mr. Holmes
否则就会惹祸上身
or be trouble under foot.
恐怕由于我们谈得太起劲
You know I'm afraid that in the pleasure
我会把别处
of this conversation I am neglecting business
等我去办的重要事情给耽搁了
of importance which awaits me elsewhere.
好吧 好吧 真遗憾
Well, well, it seems a pity
但是我已经仁至义尽
but I've done what I could.
这是你死我活的一场决斗 福尔摩斯先生
This is a duel between you and me Mr. Holmes.
你想把我置于被告席上
You hope to place me in the dark.
你想击败我
You hope to beat me.
如果你的聪明足以使我遭到毁灭
If you are clever enough to bring destruction on me,
请放心好了 你会与我同归于尽的
rest assured I shall do as much for you.
你过奖了
You have paid me several compliments,
莫里亚蒂先生
Mr. Moriarity.
让我也来回敬你一句吧
Let me pay you one in return when I say that if
如果能保证毁灭你
I were assured of the former eventuality
为了社会的利益
I would, in the interests of the public,
即使和你同归于尽 我也心甘情愿
cheerfully accept the later.
我答应与你同归于尽 但不是你毁灭我
I can promise you the one but not the other.
他是犯罪界的拿破仑 华生
He is the Napoleon of crime Watson.
几年来 我一直在努力
For years I have endeavored
抽丝剥茧
to break through the veil which shrouded him
终于 我抓住了一条线索
and at last I have seized a thread
跟着它找到了莫里亚蒂本人
and followed it to Moriarity himself.
现在 我已经撒好网等着将他绳之以法
And now I'm ready to close on him.
如果他没有先抓住你的话
If he doesn't close upon you first.
在下星期一 时机就成熟了
On Monday next, matters will be right
教授和他那一帮主要党羽
but the Professor and all the principal members
就要全部落入警察手中
of his gang will be in the hands of the police.
那时就会进行本世纪最大的刑事审判
Then will come the greatest criminal trial of the century,
40多起疑案即将破获
the clearing up of over 40 mysteries
他们将全部被判处绞刑
and the room full of them.
在逮捕前这几天
I cannot do better than to get away
我显然以离开此地为妙
for the few remaining days.
如果你愿意与我同去欧洲旅行一番
It would give me great pleasure Watson if you would come
那我就太高兴了
onto the continent with me.
去欧洲?
The continent?
我很高兴同你去 福尔摩斯 但是去哪?
I'd be delighted Holmes, but where?
随便那里
Anywhere.
对我来说都一样
It's all the same to me.
是的 但是 我们难道不应该
Yes, but won't we have to dispose of
先处理完莫里亚蒂教授的事吗?
Professor Moriarity first?
已经有人盯上这里了
It seems to me that we're under siege in this very room.
这提醒我 我必须该上路了
And that reminds me I must be on my way.
你不留一夜?
Won't you stay the night?
不 如果我留宿的话会给你造成危险的
No, it's too dangerous for you if I stay here.
我会按原路返回并且回住处
I will leave the way I came and find lodgings
找我的哥哥 迈克罗夫特
with my brother Mycroft.
我们明早动身
We start tomorrow morning.
明天早晨?
Tomorrow morning?
是的 一刻也不能耽搁
Oh, yes, it is most necessary.
这些就是给你的指令 我请你
Now here are your instructions and I beg of you
一定要不折不扣地遵照执行
to follow them to the letter.
现在我俩正在同
We are now playing a double-handed game with me,
欧洲最有势力的犯罪集团
Watson against the most powerful syndicate
作殊死的决斗
of criminals in Europe.
不管你打算带什么样的行李
You will dispatch whatever luggage
不要写地址 并于今夜派一个可靠的人
you intend to take by a trusted messenger unaddressed
送往维多利亚车站
at the Victoria Station tonight.
明天一早 你叫哈德森太太雇辆高级马车
In the morning you will send Mrs. Hudson for a handsome cab,
吩咐她不要雇第一辆
desiring her not to take the first
和第二辆主动来揽生意的马车
or second which may present itself.
用纸条写个地址交给车夫
You will drive to the Strand end of La Famules,
上面写着驶往劳瑟街斯特兰德尽头处
handing the address to the cabman
吩咐他不要丢掉纸条
but with a request that he will not throw it away.
你要事先把车费付清
Have your fare ready and the instant that your cab
马车一停 马上穿过街道
stops move speedily through the muse and time yourself
于9:15到达街的另一端
to reach the other end at exactly a quarter past 9:00
你会见到一辆四轮轿式小马车等在街边
where you will find a small broom waiting close to the curb
驾车的人的人披深黑色斗篷
driven by a fellow with a heavy black coat,
领子是红色镶边的
tipped at the collar with red.
上了车 便能及时赶到维多利亚车站
Into this you will stay and you will reach Victoria
搭乘开往欧洲大陆的快车
in time for the continental express.
打扰 先生 你会说意大利语吗?
Excuse me sir, I wonder if you speak Italian.
很遗憾 我不会
No, I'm afraid not.
我在找预定了这件隔间的先生
I'm looking for the gentleman who reserved this compartment.
没有看到他 先生
Not a sign of him sir.
如果你要旅行 你最好快上车
If you're traveling you better get aboard.
我亲爱的华生 你还没有屈尊
My dear Watson you haven't even condescended
向我道早安呢
to say good morning to me.
天哪 福尔摩斯 你可把我吓着了
Good heavens Holmes, how you startled me.
严密防范依然是必要的
It is still necessary to take every precaution.
看来我做得很好 华生
I did rather fine, Watson.
既然这是快车 而且又和轮船联运
I see that this express runs in connection with the boat
我想我们已经成功地把莫里亚蒂甩掉了
so I think we've shaken off Moriarity very effectively.
他能怎么办呢?
Well what will he do then?
我能怎么办 他就能怎么办
What I should do.
定一辆专列
Engage a special train.
可是那一定太晚了
But he'll arrive too late.
你看看火车时刻表就会知道
You'll observe from your Bradshaw that this train
这趟车要在坎特伯雷站停车
stops at Canterbury and again at the boat.
莫里亚蒂会在码头上抓住我们
Moriarity will catch us there.
天哪 那别人还以为我们是罪犯呢
Good heavens anybody would think that we were the criminals.
我们何不在他来到时先逮捕他
Let's arrest him as soon as he arrives.
不 那会前功尽弃的
No, that would ruin everything.
如果我们先抓住了大鱼
If we should catch the big fish then the smaller
那些小鱼就会横冲直撞 脱网而逃
would dart right and left out of the net.
不 不 许多余党还未浮出水面
No, no, and the rest is invisible.
那我们该怎么办?
Well what then?
我们要在坎特伯雷下车
We shall get ours at Canterbury.
那我们的行李怎么办
But Holmes our luggage.
我们必须给莫里亚蒂留点线索
We must give Moriarity something to follow.
然后呢?
What will we do?
我们作横贯全国的旅行
We shall go across country.
我们到了 福尔摩斯
Here we are Holmes,
列车表从来不会让你失望的
Bradshaw shouldn't let you down.
在阿什福德中转站 我们可以搭1点的慢车
From Ashford Junction we can take a 1:00 slow train
到达哈斯汀 然后到达亲爱的
to Hastings, then onto the dear old
老伦敦布莱顿和南海岸线
London Brighton and South Coast line,
驶过巴克斯山直达刘易斯
Bax Hill on to Lewis non-stop,
之后到达纽黑文
then onto New Haven,
坐晚班船去维也纳
evening boat to Vienna.
我想我们可以提前吃午餐
I think we've got time for an early lunch.
太快了
So soon.
你看 我们朋友的智力毕竟有限
There are limits you see to even our friend's intelligence.
现在 华生 我们该给自己
And now Watson, we shall treat ourselves
买两个毡睡袋 以便鼓励下
for a couple of carpet bags, encourage the manufacturers,
沿途国家的睡袋商
the countries through which we travel and make our way
然后从容自在地经过卢森堡
at leisure into Switzerland
和巴塞尔 到瑞士一游
via Brussels, Luxemberg...
一切都如夏洛克・福尔摩斯所预料
It fell out as Sherlock Holmes had predicted.
我们在布鲁塞尔住了两晚
We stayed two nights in Brussels,
然后悠闲地向东南方向继续旅行
then began to make our leisurely way southeast.
度过了美妙的一周
For a charming week
我们开始向阿尔卑斯山进发
we progressed towards the Alps.
你如何看待?
What do you think?
山石坠落是常有的事
A common enough occurrence in the mountains.
啊 没有比在酒的生产地品酒更惬意的了
Ah, nothing like drinking the wine where it's grown.
嗯
Hmm.
所有党羽都已抓获 只有莫里亚蒂逃脱了
All gang safely secured, only Moriarity escaped the net,
迈克罗夫特写来的
signed Mycroft.
他溜走了
He's given them the slip.
我想最好
I think it would be better if you were to
你还是回英国去 华生
return to England Watson.
为什么?
Why?
现在你和我作伴已经很危险了
You will find me a very dangerous companion now.
莫里亚蒂会竭尽全力
Moriarity will devote all his energies to taking his
报复我 而如果我有个同伴...
revenge upon me and if I have a companion...
你想甩我?
Would you be rid of me?
不 但这次是迫不得已
No, except for the reasons I've given.
我们已经经历过许多磨难
We've been in tight places before together.
但没有一个像这次这样艰难
Never as tight as this one.
我不会离开你 的 福尔摩斯
I'm not leaving you Holmes,
除非你命令我离开
not unless you order me to go.
我以前从没来过瑞士
I've never been to Switzerland before
但是这些美景使我不由自主地想起
but the beauty of the landscape reminded me irresistibly
那些印度西北边境的省区
of the northwest frontier provinces of India.
但是 尽管周围的景色如此优美
But in spite of the lovely scenery all around us,
我心里非常清楚 夏洛克・福尔摩斯
it was clear to me that never for one instant
心中的阴影
did Sherlock Holmes forget the shadow
一刻都没有消失过
that lay across him.
我可以从他警惕的神情中看出
I could tell by his sharp scrutiny of every face
他非常清楚 无论我们走到那里
that he was well convinced that go where we would
危险都会一直尾随
we would not be clear of the danger
绝不会消除
that was dogging our footsteps.
那是什么?
What was that?
看见什么了吗?
See anything?
不 什么都没
No, nothing.
是时候继续上路了
It's time we went on our way.
汉斯 我们上路了
Hans, we're on our way.
最后我们到达了博那斯小镇的心脏地带
At last we reached the heart of the burnice overland
来到了迈林根的一个小村镇
and came to the village of Mirengland
我们在"大英旅馆"下榻
where we put up at the Englisher Hall
旅馆的主人是老彼得・斯太勒
then kept by Peter Steiler the Elder.
啊 斯太勒?
Uh, Steiler?
翻山到达罗森洛依 一路上的风景迷人
The walk over to the hills to Rosenlawry is very beautiful.
你们可以在那过夜 第二天再回来
You can stay the night there and come back the next day
不要错过莱辛巴赫瀑布
but you must not on any account miss
可以稍微绕一些路去欣赏一番
the falls of Reichenbach which is only a small detour.
啊 就是那了
Uh, there it is.
那确实是一个险恶的地方
It is indeed a fearful place.
融雪汇成激流
The torrent, swollen by the melting glacier,
倾泻进万丈深渊 水花高溅
plunges into a tremendous abyss in which the spray rose up
宛如房屋失火时冒出的浓烟
like the smoke from a burning house.
华生医生
Herr, Dr. Watson.
什么事?
Yes?
斯太勒先生让我把这个交给你
Herr Steiler told me to give you this.
非常紧急
It is very urgent.
好像是一个英国妇女在我们离开以后
It seems an English woman was taken to the hotel
被送到了旅馆 她正要去卢塞恩访友
after we left on her way to friends in Lucerne.
不料她突然咯血
She's had a great hemorrhage.
是肺结核
Tuberculoses.
那是肯定的
Oh, no doubt.
她颇有生命危险
It appears she's dying.
如有位英国医生为她诊治 她会十分欣慰
An English doctor would be a great consolation.
恐怕我必须回去了 福尔摩斯
I'm afraid I must go back Holmes.
那是当然
Of course.
斯太勒还建议你让这个小伙子给你带路
Steiler suggests that this lad shows you the way
去罗森洛依 我稍后和你们会合
to Rosenlawy and I'll join you there later.
不错的计划
A good plan.
嘿!
Hey!
她病情没有恶化吧?
I trust she's no worse.
?????
你没有写这封信吗?
You didn't write this?
旅馆里没有一位生病的英国女人吗?
There is no sick English woman at the hotel?
可是这上面有旅馆的印章
No, but it has the hotel mark.
当然 这一定是那高个子英国人写的
Of course, there was a tall old Englishman
他在你们走之后过来的
who came here after you had gone.
他说
He said...
看到登山杖
It was the sight of the Alpine stalk
不由使我不寒而栗
that turned me cold and sick.
他并没有去罗森洛依
He had not gone to Rosenlawy.
我在那站了一两分钟 平复自己的心情
I stood for a minute or two to collect myself
因为我被这件事吓昏了头
for I was dazed with the horror of the thing.
然后开始想起福尔摩斯的方法
And then I began to think of Holmes' own methods
竭力运用它去查明这场悲剧
and to try to practice them.
福尔摩斯
Holmes,
Holmes.
我亲爱的华生 承蒙莫里亚蒂先生的好意
My Dear Watson, I write these few lines
我写下这几行书信
through the courtesy of Mr. Moriarity
他正等着对我们之间存在的问题
who awaits my convenience for the final discussion
进行最后的讨论
of those questions which lie between us.
我一想到我能为社会除掉
I'm pleased to think that I shall be able
由于他的存在而带来的祸害 就很高兴
to free society from any further affects of his presence.
虽然 这恐怕要以给我的朋友们
Though I fear that it is at a cost
带来痛苦为代价
which will give pain to my friends
尤其是给你 我亲爱的华生
and especially my dear Watson,
带来悲哀
to you.
正如你所知 我的生涯已经
As you know, my career had in any case
到了紧要关头
reached a crisis.
而对我而言 没有比这
And no possible conclusion to it could be more congenial
更令我心满意足的结局了
to me than this.
诚然 如果我对你彻底坦白说
Indeed if I may make a full confession to you,
我早就知道那封信
I was convinced that the letter...
是一场骗局
was a hoax.
在离开英国时
I made every disposition of my property
我已将薄产作了处理
before leaving England
并已付与我兄迈克罗夫特
and handed it to my brother Mycroft.
再见 好运
Good bye and good luck
你是我最亲爱的朋友
and believe me to be my dear fellow,
你忠诚的夏洛克 福尔摩斯
very sincerely yours, Sherlock Holmes.
毫无疑问 在这种情况下
In this situation I have little doubt
那两人之间的斗争
that a personal contest between the two men
已经结束 因为它已无法继续
ended as it could hardly fail to end.
啊!
Ahh!
我怀着无比沉重的心情提起笔
It's with a heavy heart that I take up my pen
最后写下我的朋友
to write these last words in which I shall ever record
福尔摩斯先生所拥有的
singular gifts by which my friend
卓越才能
Mr. Sherlock Holmes was distinguished.
我会永远把他视为
I shall ever regard him
我所知道的
as the best and wisest man
最优秀 最睿智的人
I have ever known.
-==www.RagBear.com==-